Guide to the Edward R. Murrow Photographs 1909-1964
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Edward R. Murrow Photographs
1909-1964
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections Pullman, WA 99164-5610 USA (509) 335-6691 https://libraries.wsu.edu/masc/ mascref@wsu.edu
PC 30
Murrow, Edward R.
1 container. .5 linear feet of shelf space. 130 items.
The collection consists of ninety-eight black and white photographs, one black and white montage, and two color photographs of Edward R. Murrow. Images span Murrow's life, from boyhood scenes to college, and through his career with CBS. Also included are three pieces of correspondence addressed to E.R. or Janet Murrow, a New York Times advertisement for E.R. Murrow and CBS, and three articles from the news magazines Time, Look, and Newsweek. A collection of twenty-two black and white photographs taken in 1942 by the Hutchison Studio, Pullman, Washington, has been added to the Murrow collection.
Edward [Egbert] Roscoe Murrow was born on April 25, 1908, near Greensboro, North Carolina. He was the youngest of three boys born to Roscoe and Ethel Murrow. The family moved to Blanchard, Washington when Murrow was five. Subsequently, Murrow attended Washington State College in Pullman, Washington, graduating in 1930. He was president of the National Student Federation from 1929 to 1932 and assistant director of the Institute of International Education from 1932 to 1935. In 1934 he married Janet Brewster. Their son, Charles Casey, was born November 6, 1945, in West London.
Murrow was hired by CBS in 1935 and worked for them until 1961. During those years he worked as war correspondent in London, 1939 to 1945, vice president, director of public affairs, 1945 to 1947, and news analyst and host for the television programs Person to Person, See It Now, and Small World during the 1950s. He was on the CBS board of directors from 1949 to 1955. In 1961, Edward R. Murrow was appointed director of the United States Information Agency (USIA), serving until 1964. He died on April 27, 1965.
The collection donated by Janet Murrow consists of ninety-eight black and white photographs, one black and white montage, and two color photographs of Edward R. Murrow. Included are three pieces of correspondence addressed to E.R. or Janet Murrow, a New York Times advertisement for E.R. Murrow and CBS, and three articles from the news magazines Time, Look, and Newsweek. A collection of twenty-two black and white photographs taken in 1942 by the Hutchison Studio, Pullman, Washington, has been added to the Murrow collection.
This collection is open for research use.
The E.R. Murrow photographs were donated to the Washington State University Library by Janet (Brewster) Murrow, of South Hadley, Massachusetts in two accessions, in January and March of 1978 (78-2).
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Murrow, Edward R. --Archives; Murrow, Edward R.--Portraits
Hutchison Studio; Historical Photograph Collections. waps
Photographs; Journalism; Washington (State)
Group portraits -- Washington (State)--20th century. gmgpc waps; Montages--20th century. gmgpc waps; Portraits--Washington (State)--20th century. gmgpc waps
Radio journalists -- United States--Portraits; Television journalists --United States--Portraits
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- "London/NYC, returning from London.", 1939-1945
  - ERM with Bill Hewey, CBS office, London., 1939 (Folder a, Item 1)
  - ERM on London street., 1940 (Folder a, Item 2)
  - ERM on London street., 1940; 83-114 (Folder a, Item 3)
  - ERM with three war correspondents., circa 1940; 83-117 (Folder a, Item 4)
  - ERM with unidentified bomber pilot., circa 1941; 92-181 (Folder a, Item 5)
  - ERM on deck of ship arriving in NYC, from London., 1941 (Folder a, Item 6)
  - ERM and James Doolittle [?]., 1942-1943 (Folder a, Item 7)
  - ERM at work in London office., 1940; 83-115 (Folder a, Item 8)
  - ERM at work in London office., 1940; 79-130 (Folder a, Item 9)
  - ERM at work in London office., 1940; 83-116 (Folder a, Item 10)
  - ERM at work in London office., circa 1941 (Folder a, Item 11)
  - ERM at work in London office., May 1944 (Folder a, Item 12)
  - ERM in cockpit of fighter plane., 1944; 83-118 (Folder a, Item 13)
  - ERM with Marshall Yarrow., D-Day + 40 hrs; 85-039 (Folder a, Item 14)
- Chicago, Washington D.C., Philadelphia, Paris., 1945-1949
  - ERM with William L. Shirer., circa 1945; 83-119 (Folder b, Item 1)
  - ERM in Chicago., 1945; 83-121 (Folder b, Item 2)
  - ERM and H. Leslie Atlass (CBS Vice President in charge of Central Division) receiving Alfred I. du Pont Radio Awards from Dr. Francis P. Gaines., 1947; 85-040 (Folder b, Item 3)
  - ERM, Robert Evans, and John Adams (CBS newsmen) at the White House following Murrow's talk with President Truman., Dec. 12, 1947 (Folder b, Item 4)
  - ERM, Howard K. Smith, and other members of CBS news crew at Republican Convention, Philadelphia., 1948 (Folder b, Item 5)
  - ERM and R. Runyon. (Folder b, Item 6)
  - ERM with two SHAPE generals (unidentified), Paris [?]. (Folder b, Item 7)
  - ERM with Thomas Dewey., circa 1948 (Folder b, Item 8)
  - ERM with Thomas Dewey, Lowell Thomas and others., circa 1949 (Folder b, Item 9)
  - Informal portrait of ERM at work., circa 1949; 83-125 (Folder b, Item 10)
  - Informal portrait of ERM at work., circa 1949; 83-120 (Folder b, Item 11)
- Korea., 1952
  - ERM with Larry LeSueur., 83-059 (Folder c, Item 1)
  - ERM with Bill Downs., 83-123 (Folder c, Item 2)
  - ERM with unidentified troops., 83-124 (Folder c, Item 3)
  - ERM with Howard K. Smith., 83-122 (Folder c, Item 4)
- USA/London., 1952-1959
  - ERM with General Omar Bradley., circa early 1950s; 83-126 (Folder d, Item 1)
  - ERM, Howard K. Smith, Eric Sevareid, and David Schoenbrun, Year End Show. (Folder d, Item 2)
  - ERM with Janet Murrow and Harry Truman, Isla Magordo., 1957; 83-127 (Folder d, Item 3)
  - ERM with President Truman and others. (Folder d, Item 4)
  - ERM waiting for a Person to Person show. (Folder d, Item 5)
  - ERM on the set of Person to Person show., circa 1954-1959; 95-103 (Folder d, Item 6)
  - ERM about to go on air, Person to Person show. (Folder d, Item 7)
  - ERM, John Aaron, and Jesse Zousmer (co-producers of Person to Person show)., circa 1953-1959; 95-102 (Folder d, Item 8)
  - ERM in viewing room See It Now, 9th Avenue, NYC., 1953; 83-128 (Folder d, Item 9)
  - ERM and Fred Friendly (co-producers of See It Now)., 1953; 85-038 (Folder d, Item 10)
  - ERM with Eleanor Roosevelt and Marion Anderson., 1958; 85-041 (Folder d, Item 11)
  - ERM with Larry LeSueur., 1955; 83-129 (Folder d, Item 12)
  - ERM in 485 Madison Avenue office., 1952; 83-062 (Folder d, Item 13)
  - ERM at work in 485 Madison Avenue office with Dorothy MacDonough taking dictation., 1952; 83-130 (Folder d, Item 14)
  - ERM on set of See It Now., 1952; 79-131 (Folder d, Item 15)
  - ERM on set of See It Now., circa 1953; 79-132 (Folder d, Item 16)
  - ERM at Cape Cod, unidentified military base., summer 1952; 83-060 (Folder d, Item 17)
  - ERM at Cape Cod, unidentified military base., summer 1952 (Folder d, Item 18)
  - ERM at Cape Cod, unidentified military base., summer 1952 (Folder d, Item 19)
  - ERM with broadcasters in London., circa 1952; 83-151 (Folder d, Item 21)
- USIA/White House., 1961-1964
  - Twentieth anniversary of American Library in London. ERM with Janet Murrow, Hamish Hamilton, Cyril Connelly, and Mr. and Mrs. Yehudi Menuhin., circa 1961; 83-132 (Folder e, Item 1)
  - ERM in Tehran, Iran with Prime Minister Asadollah Alam. (Folder e, Item 2)
  - The Dytchley Conference in Oxfordshire, England. ERM with (left to right) Sir Harold Caccia, Professor John Hope Franklin, and Minister Lewis Jones. (Folder e, Item 3)
  - ERM with President John Kennedy and others in the White House [NOTE: White House letterhead regarding this photo, neg. 83-133, in Folder P, Correspondence]., circa 1961; 83-133 (Folder e, Item 4)
  - ERM with President John Kennedy (color print) (b/w neg.)., 1961; 83-134 (Folder e, Item 5)
  - ERM, Chester Bowles, Macharios, and Phillips Talbot., July 31, 1961 (Folder e, Item 6)
  - ERM with General Lauris Norstad., Aug. 7, 1961 (Folder e, Item 7)
  - ERM with Franklin Roosevelt, Jr. and Robert Dixon, Pawling, N.Y., 1961 (Folder e, Item 8)
  - ERM and Mayor Willi Brandt. (Folder e, Item 9)
  - ERM (as director of USIA) in USIA office. (Folder e, Item 10)
  - ERM with Adlai Stevenson in U.N. Studio. (Folder e, Item 11)
  - Last visit to the White House, photos by Yoichi Okamoto., circa Dec. 1963-Jan. 1964
    - ERM and President Lyndon Johnson., 83-135 (Folder e, Item 12)
    - ERM leaving the Oval Office., 83-136 (Folder e, Item 13)
    - ERM leaving the White House., 83-137 (Folder e, Item 14)
- Studio Portraits., 1941-1959
  - ERM, while home on leave., 1941; 88-343 (Folder f, Item 1)
  - ERM., circa 1948-1950 (Folder f, Item 2)
  - ERM., circa 1950 (Folder f, Item 3)
  - ERM (same image as f3)., circa 1950 (Folder f, Item 4)
- Photos of Family and Friends., 1909-1964
  - ERM at about one year of age., 1909; 83-138 (Folder g, Item 1)
  - ERM on the Olympic Peninsula as a young man, fishing., undated; 89-263 (Folder g, Item 2)
  - ERM, high school portrait., undated; 89-264 (Folder g, Item 3)
  - ERM with friends, walking from Pullman to Moscow. (Left to right) Esther Stilson, George Stapleton, Betty Ramsbeck, ERM., 1927; 88-189 (Folder g, Item 4)
  - ERM and Janet Murrow, London., 1938; 83-139 (Folder g, Item 5)
  - ERM's parents, Roscoe and Ethel Murrow, listening to ERM broadcasting from London., circa 1939-1945; 89-265 (Folder g, Item 6)
  - Murrow family gathering in Seattle., 1941; 83-150 (Folder g, Item 7)
  - ERM, Janet Murrow, and son Casey on return to U.S. at end of war., 1947; 83-142 (Folder g, Item 8)
  - Dewey J. Murrow, elder brother of ERM., undated; 89-267 (Folder g, Item 9)
  - Lacey V. Murrow, elder brother of ERM., undated; 89-268 (Folder g, Item 10)
  - ERM with brothers, Dewey J. and Lacey V. Murrow, Quaker Hill, Pawling, N.Y., 1949; 89-266 (Folder g, Item 11)
  - ERM and son Casey, Rumblewood, Pawling, N.Y., 1952; 83-148 (Folder g, Item 12)
  - ERM, Janet Murrow, and son Casey, Glen Arden Farm., 1955; 83-140 (Folder g, Item 13)
  - ERM and son Casey, Glen Arden Farm., 1955; 83-145 (Folder g, Item 14)
  - ERM and son Casey., undated; 83-144 (Folder g, Item 15)
  - ERM and son Casey, Glen Arden Farm., 1956; 83-146 (Folder g, Item 16)
  - ERM and son Casey, Wisconsin., summer 1957; 83-143 (Folder g, Item 17)
  - ERM and son Casey, Wisconsin., summer 1957; 83-147 (Folder g, Item 18)
  - ERM and son Casey, Wisconsin., summer 1957 (Folder g, Item 19)
  - ERM with Janet Murrow and son Casey, Stockholm., Sept. 1959; 83-141 (Folder g, Item 20)
- Informal Portraits at Home: Glen Arden Farm Rumblewood, both at Quaker Hill, Pawling, N.Y., 1947-1964
  - ERM reading on couch., 1947 (Folder h, Item 1)
  - ERM at Rumblewood., 1950 (Folder h, Item 2)
  - ERM at Rumblewood., 1952 (Folder h, Item 3)
  - ERM at Rumblewood., 1952; 79-153 (Folder h, Item 4)
  - ERM at Rumblewood., 1952 (Folder h, Item 5)
  - ERM., 1954 (Folder h, Item 6)
  - ERM in dairy, Glen Arden Farm., undated (Folder h, Item 7)
  - ERM at Glen Arden Farm., circa 1955-1956 (Folder h, Item 8)
  - ERM at Glen Arden Farm., 1955 (Folder h, Item 9)
  - ERM at La Jolla, recovering from first operation., 1964 (Folder h, Item 10)
- Undated Photographs.
  - ERM, informal portrait. (Folder i, Item 1)
  - ERM with two unidentified men. (Folder i, Item 2)
- Photo Montage: Just how long is a sabbatical, Ed?, 1959 (Folder j)
- Hutchison Studio, Pullman, Washington, PC 70. Two series, 14048 and 5131-33., 29 January 1942; May 1946
  - Hutchison Studio, Pullman, Washington, from PC 70 #14048. Six formal portraits of Edward R. Murrow, two copies of each, 1942 (Hutchison print) and 1997 ( WSU Photo Lab, Holland Library)., 29 January 1942 (Folder k, Item a1-a6)
  - Maynard Lee Daggy (center), head of Speech Department in 1942, ERM (left), Elden Barr (right), blind radio announcer., 97-037 (Folder k, Item b1)
  - ERM visiting Kappa Sigma fraternity, State College of Washington., 1942; 97-038 (Folder k, Item b2)
  - ERM with radio buddies John McCollom and Bob Curtis., 1942; 97-039 (Folder k, Item b3)
  - ERM with members of National Collegiate Radio Guild., May 1946; 97-040 (Folder k, Item b4)
  - George Holt (left), Joe Ashlock (center, then head of Journalism) and ERM contemplating NCRG award., 97-041 (Folder k, Item b5)
  - George Holt (left), ERM, Joe Ashlock (right) at Kappa Sigma reception., 1942; 97-042 (Folder k, Item b6)
  - ERM speaking at welcoming banquet sponsored by Sigma Delta Phi, just after return from London., 1942; 97-043 (Folder k, Item b7)
  - ERM speaking at welcoming banquet., 1942; 97-047 (Folder k, Item b8)
  - President Holland and ERM acknowledging greeting from audience of 6,000, Bohler Gym., 1942; 97-049 (Folder k, Item b9)
  - ERM speaking at Bohler Gym (with duplicate)., 1942; 97-048 (Folder k, Item b10)
  - ERM visiting his alma mater (Washington State College), at Bohler Gym, with President Holland (right)., 97-044 (Folder k, Item b11)
  - President Holland and ERM waiting for applause to cease, Bohler Gym., 1942; 97-050 (Folder k, Item b12)
  - Welcoming banquet for ERM, sponsored by Sigma Delta Phi; with President Holland, his sister Mrs. Rundell, ERM, Wyman Cox, MC (chairman of DSF meeting)., 97-045 (Folder k, Item b13)
  - Welcoming banquet for ERM, with President Holland, his sister Mrs. Rundell, ERM, Wyman Cox, MC., 97-046 (Folder k, Item b14)
  - Welcoming banquet for ERM. Murrow can barely be seen, seated between Mrs. Rundell and Wyman Cox, MC (man reaching across table)., 97-051 (Folder k, Item b15)
  - Informal portrait of ERM., 88-322 (Folder k, Item c1)
  - ERM at KWSC podium., 88-342 (Folder k, Item c2)
  - ERM with five fraternity brothers, all in 1930 sweaters. (Folder k, Item c3)
- Publications., 1948-1961
  - [7/18/2017 - item missing. MOE.] Advertisement for ERM and CBS. The New York Times., April 9, 1948; 83- 113 (Folder l)
  - Article, Time., September 30, 1957 (Folder m)
  - Article, Look., August 18, 1959 (Folder n)
  - Article, Newsweek., September 18, 1961 (Folder o)
- Correspondence., 1963; 1978
  - Letterhead from United States Advisory Commission on Information, Washington, D.C. to ERM from J. Leonard Reinsch, regarding picture (neg. 83-133) of ERM and President John Kennedy [see Folder E #4]., March 14, 1963 (Folder p, Item 1)
  - Letter to Janet Murrow from Olga E. Allers, M.D., regarding reunion., Jan. 17, 1978 (Folder p, Item 2)
  - Letter to Janet Murrow from Evis Towle Jennings, regarding reunion., Feb. 2, 1978 (Folder p, Item 3)